Domenico Facci
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Domenico Facci papers
1914-1995
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Facci, Domenico
1.2 linear feet
The Domenico Facci papers are dated 1914 to 1995, with the bulk falling between the years 1950 and 1984. They measure 1.2 linear feet and consist of biographical material, correspondence, artwork relating to sculpture projects, printed material, and photographs. Among the well-documented aspects of Facci's professional career are: his leadership roles in several arts organizations based in New York City, including Audubon Artists, National Sculpture Society, and Artists Equity Association; his work on the United States Treasury's 1988 Olympic Games commemorative coin competition, Brooklyn Bridge 100th Anniversary reliefs, Endangered Species Medal, and Neptune Fountain at Busch Gardens in Williamsburg, VA.
Provenance
Gift of Debby Friedman, 2010.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Domenico Facci (1914-1994) worked in New York City and was known primarily for commissioned portraits and public sculpture, and for holding leadership positions in several arts organizations based in New York City.
Domenico (Aurelio) Facci was born in Hooversville, Pennsylvania on February 2, 1916, where his father, Antonio, was a coal miner. His mother was Grace Facci. Domenico was one of ten children, and when he was ten years old the family moved to Brooklyn, New York.
Facci won a scholarship to Roerich Academy (Master Institute of United Arts) where he studied under Pietro Montana and Louis Slobodkin and graduated in 1936. In 1937 he opened his first studio on Fifth Avenue at 15th Street and was immediately commissioned to do several large pieces for the 1939 World's Fair.
Many public and private commissions were executed by Facci in the New York City area, among them: carvings on the tower façade of St. Thomas's church, St. Rita sculpture in Long Island City, lobby for American Express building, 100 feet of plaques on the Brooklyn Bridge walkway, and bronze sculptures for PS 147 in the Bronx. Facci was also awarded portrait commissions of eminent public figures including: Winston Churchill, Albert Einstein, Bob Hope, Lowell Thomas, James Kilpatrick, and Lynn Redgrave, some of which were executed on live television and at other events. Some important commissions in other locations were: a cartouche for bronze doors for St Peter's Cathedral, Philadelphia, PA; exterior bronze for the Court of Appeals Building, Annapolis, MD; St. Paul sculpture, Fredericksburg, MD; Eagle War Monument, Rome, NY; and St. John Divine in Sewanee, TN.
Facci was the recipient of numerous important awards, including the Proctor Award from the National Academy of Design, the Richards Award from the Allied Artists, and the Liskin Award from the Knickerbocker Artists. He was also elected a fellow of the National Sculpture Society. Solo exhibitions of Facci's work were presented at the Silvermine Guild of Artists and the Village Art Center. He participated in group shows at the Whitney Museum of American Art and the National Academy of Design, Jersey City. Facci exhibited annually at numerous New York artists organization, including the Village Art Center, Knickerbocker Artists, and at the Silvermine Guild.
Facci's work is included in the permanent collections of the Florida Southern College, in Lakeland, FL, the Norfolk Museum, VA, and the Polk Museum, FL.
As an active member of numerous professional artists organizations, Facci served as the president of the Village Art Center for a decade, president of the Audubon Artists for 11 years, and president of the American Society of Contemporary Artists. In addition, he was an officer in other organizations, including: Knickerbocker Artists, Allied Artists, New Jersey Painters and Sculptors, National Sculpture Society, Silvermine Guild of Artists, New York Artists' Equity Association, Sculptors League, Salmagundi Club, National Academy of Design, and the American Society of Contemporary Artists.
In addition to his work as a sculptor, Facci was also a teacher. Between 1939 and 1972, he served on the faculty of City College of New York, the Academy of Art at Florida Southern College, Ridgewood Village Art School in New Jersey, and the Craft Student League in New York.
Domenico Facci was married to Penelope (Felicia/ Penny) Facci and they had a son, Robert. Domenico Facci died on November 6, 1994.
Scope and Content Note
The Domenico Facci papers are dated 1914 to 1995, with the bulk falling between the years 1950 and 1984. They measure 1.2 linear feet and consist of biographical material, correspondence, artwork relating to sculpture projects, printed material, and photographs. Among the well-documented aspects of Facci's professional career are: his leadership rolses in several arts organizations based in New York City, including Audubon Artists, National Sculpture Society, and Artists Equity Association; his work on the United States Treasury's 1988 Olympic Games commemorative coin competition, Brooklyn Bridge 100th Anniversary reliefs, Endangered Species Medal, and Neptune Fountain at Busch Gardens in Williamsburg, VA.
Biographical material consists of artist's statements; marriage, academic, and military service records; awards; and membership cards and certificates. Correspondence consists mainly of incoming letters related to Facci's activities with arts organizations, among them Audubon Artists, American Society of Contemporary Artists, the Village Art Center, Artists Equity Association, the National Sculpture Society, and Nippon Museum.
Artwork includes two sketchbooks - one for the 1988 Olympic Games commemorative coin competition, and another concerning the Endangered Species Medal. Also found are anatomical study drawings, blueprint plans for the Neptune Fountain project, and miscellaneous sketches.
Printed materials are newspaper clippings, newsletters, exhibition catalogs, programs, press releases, announcements, and brochures. The bulk of this series is comprised of exhibition catalogs from the Audubon Artists, Painters and Sculptors Society of New Jersey, National Arts Club, and National Sculpture Society.
Photographs are of Facci and his work, including completed pieces, the artist at work in his studio and presenting sculpture demonstrations.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1914-1998 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 2. Correspondence, 1954-1988 (Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 3. Artwork, circa 1930-1985 (Box 1; OV 2-3; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 4. Printed Material, 1933-1988 (Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 5. Scrapbook, circa 1940-1985 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 6. Photographs, circa 1940-1985 (Box 1; 0.2 linear ft.)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
American Society of Contemporary Artists (New York, N.Y.); Artists Equity Association; Audubon Artists (New York, N.Y.); National Sculpture Society (U.S.); United States.--Dept. of the Treasury; Olympic Games--(24th: 1988: Seoul, Korea)
Subjects-Topical:
Art--Economic aspects; Artists' studios; Medalists--New York (State)--New York; Sculptors--New York (State)--New York
Subjects-Geographical:
Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.); BuschGardens (Williamsburg, Va.)
Types of Materials:
Awards; Blueprints; Photographs; Sketchbooks
Names:
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Records1914-1998, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
  Family papers relating to both of Domenico Facci's parents consist of business records, marriage certificates, and funeral and burial arrangements. Resumes and personal records include artist resumes, artist's statements, entries for Who's Who, marriage certificate. Among the educational records are report cards, letters of recommendation, and the announcement of his Roerich Academy of Art (Master Institute of United Arts) scholarship. Military service records include letter of call for duty, assignment posts, application for specialist qualification, and letters from the Veterans Administration. Award and memberships include membership cards and certificates, the Proctor Prize from the National Academy of Design, and awards from New York Artists Equity Association, Kappa Pi, Sigma Phi Epsilon, Silvermine Guild of Artists, Brooklyn Society of Artists, Jersey City Museum, Knickerbocker Artists, Audubon Artists, Allied Artists of America, and others.
  - Family Papers,1914-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes and Documents, 1921-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Educational Records, 1933-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Military Service, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards and Memberships, 1930-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence,1954-1988, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.)
  The majority of correspondence consists of incoming letters; the only reciprocal exchanges preserved are with Penelope Facci and his friend Donna Stoddard. Family correspondence includes mostly letters between Penelope and Domenico, a letter from their son Robert, and one from from Guiseppe Facci, a distant relative. The bulk of the incoming letters relate to Domenico Facci's membership and leadership activities with arts organizations such as Audubon Artists, American Society of Contemporary Artists, the Village Art Center, Artists Equity Association, National Sculpture Society, and the Nippon Museum. Also found are personal letters, invitations, and holiday cards.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically.
  - Added Touch - American Society of Contemporary Artists, 1952-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Audubon Artists, 1956-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Barker, Al - Cooper, Dale Meyer, 1943-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dake, Walter - Ettl, Alex, 1952-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Facci Family,1930-1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Guiseppe
    Penelope
    Robert
  - Fazzano, Joseph - Italian Culture Council, 1940-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Joshi, Satish - Long Beach Monument Co., 1954-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mamaroneck Artists Guild - National Commemorative Society, 1954-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - National Sculpture Society, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Nippon Museum, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Painters and Sculptors Society of New Jersey - Quirk and Bakalor, 1942-1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Raben, Ether - Steep Rock Wildlife Art, 1943-1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Stoddard, Donna, 1960-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Thomas, Lowell - Viewpoint Productions, 1951-1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Washington Square Business and Professional Women's Club - Yeshiva University, 1953-1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Unidentified, 1966-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Carey N.
    Cathie
    Diana
    Elizabeth
    Gail
    Jae
    Jeanie
    Jen
    Lois
    Marc
    Rose and Ruth
    Theresa
    Tina
- Artwork, circa 1930s- 1988, Series 3:; (Box 1; OV 2-3; 0.3 linear ft.)
  This series includes two sketchbooks of studies - one for the 1988 Olympic Games commemorative coin competition sponsored by the United States Treasury, and another containing drawings for the Endangered Species Medal. Also found are watercolor and pencil sketches of models and animals, anatomical and portrait studies, illustrations, cartoons, and sketches for an eagle medal, along with blueprint plans for the Neptune Fountain, in Busch Gardens, Williamsburg, VA.
  - Drawings, circa 1930, (removed from binder; original collation retained) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sketches and Watercolors, 1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sketchbooks (Box 1)
    - 1988 Olympic Games Coin Competition, 1988, (1 volume) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Endangered Species Medal, undated, (1 volume) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Endangered Species Medal and Other Sketches,undated (Box OV 2)
  - Neptune Fountain,1976, (3 blueprints) (Box OV 3)
- Printed Materials, 1933 - 1988, Series 4:; (Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.)
  Printed materials consist of newspaper and magazine articles, newsletters, exhibition catalogs, programs, press releases and announcements, and brochures. The majority of the exhibition catalogs are from the Audubon Artists, Painters and Sculptors Society of New Jersey, National Arts Club, and National Sculpture Society. Listings of Facci's work seen on e-Bay are also included.
  Exhibition catalogs are arranged alphabetically by sponsoring organizatin. Additional printed items can be found in Series 5, Scrapbook.
  - Articles, 1933-1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Newsletters and Bulletins, 1952-1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - e-Bay Listings, 2002-2008 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Brochures, 1945-1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1954-1988, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 30-33)
- Scrapbook, circa 1940 - 1985, Series 5:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  The scrapbook contains newspaper clippings and photographs of Facci's finished work, clay models, and the sculptor at work.
  - Scrapbook, circa 1940-1985, (removed from 3 ring binder) (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Photographs, circa 1940 - 1985, Series 6:; (Box 1; 0.2 linear ft.)
  Photographs, mainly black and white, are of artwork, people and events.
  Photographs of Facci include portraits of the sculptor and views of him in the company of friends and family. In addition, he is shown at work in his studio and while demonstrating the sculptural process. Among the photographs of live demonstrations are Facci sculpting John DeLurie and Lowell Thomas. Other pictures of people are family photographs from social gatherings and celebrations.
  Among the photographs of artwork are Facci's finished sculpture, clay models, and related studies. Also found are views of work and installations in progress, among them the Brooklyn Bridge 100th Anniversary reliefs, Neptune Fountain, and unidentified projects. Also found is a photograph of a portrait of Domenico Facci painted by Byron Browne.
  Events recorded include and East West Evening with Pearl Buck held at the White House in 1945, and an unidentified costume ball.
  - People - Domenico Facci (Box 1)
    - Portraits, circa 1940-1985 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - With Friends, Family and Others, circa 1940-1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - At Work in Studio, circa 1940-1985 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Sculpture Demonstrations, 1971, circa 1940-1985 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - People - Others, circa 1940-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Artwork by Domenico Facci (Box 1)
    - Animals,undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Figures, 1965-1977 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Heads, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Reliefs, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Miscellaneous Subjects, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Brooklyn Bridge in Progress, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Neptune Fountain in Progress, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Unidentified Projects in Progress, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Artwork by Byron Browne, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Events (Box 1)
    - East West Evening,1945 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Costume Ball (Artists Equity Ball ?), undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Dedication of Brooklyn Bridge Plaques, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Negative of Unidentified Artwork,undated (Box 1, Folder 52)